Finding Aid for Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1920-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.) records 1920-2008
Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.).
2 linear feet
90173 Ba 2
African-American Baptist congregation located in Detroit, MI.; also called Shiloh Baptist Church. The record group includes a church history, celebratory and obsequy programs, clippings, and notebooks of materials accumulated during the pastorates of R. B. James, Solomon David Ross, William H. Crews, and Harold Knox; also bulletins of church services.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the church (donor no. 7815 ) in various installments beginning in 1990.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church is the second oldest African-American Baptist congregation in Detroit and was founded in 1881 by the Reverend John Wills; at its founding, there were 25 members.
The church at the Benton Street site was designed by a black draftsman--Carlos N. Stokes--in 1920, but the church was not completed until 1926 when the congregation moved from their previous church in the Eastern Market.
Reverend Solomon Ross was called to the pastoral vacancy in 1929 (following Reverend Robert James' death) and was integral to the church's survival in the depression years. In 1931 he detected fraud among some of the church officials, and had more than 50 members expelled. In 1935, Reverend Ross fought the federal government's attempt to raze the church. He succeeded in his fight and this explains the seemingly unusual location of the church within the Brewster Project. In 1937, Ross organized a Junior Church to train the children in running the church as they grew older. Ross would continue to facilitate African-American progress and opportunities well into the 1960s.
Reverend William Crews was called after Ross' passing, and served through 2003. Crews helped triple the number of people who tithed in Shiloh, and engaged in interstate visitation for the first time in its history. In 1977, Crews and the congregation engaged in a massive remodeling of Shiloh, modernizing the building throughout. Reverend Crews engaged in another renovation project, this time to construct the Mary O. Ross Education Building. In 1981, Shiloh celebrated its Centennial Anniversary, with a special banquet and program of events.
In 2003, Reverend Harold Lee Knox was installed as pastor, though he would come into conflict with the congregation and the deacons of the church two years later. Knox resigned as pastor in 2007 after legal proceedings.
The church is a large, redbrick, one-story building resting upon a concrete pod with limestone trim. In the front, a major addition was constructed in 1978. This is a large two-story brick entryway with a flat roof. In the Eric Hill, John Gallagher book, AIA Detroit: The American Institute of Architects Guide to Detroit Architecture (Wayne State University Press, 2003) one can find a sketch of the original entrance designed by Carlos Stokes. It is a classical church entrance strongly influenced by traditional European church architecture.
The Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church records includes a church history, celebratory and obsequy programs, clippings, and notebooks of materials accumulated during the pastorates of R. B. James, Solomon David Ross, William H. Crews, and Harold Knox; also bulletins of church services. The record group consists of four series: Church Publications, History, Topical File, and Miscellaneous Records.
Subjects:
African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Crews, William H.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; James, Robert B.; Knox, Harold.; Ross, Solomon David.; Greater Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
- Church Publications
  The Church Publications series contains newsletters from 1929, and a selection of bulletins from the 21st century.
  - Bulletins, 2001-2008, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1929 (Box 1)
- History
  The History series is organized chronologically, and is organized under the pastor of those relevant years. It ends with a general history, including a book describing the church's first 100 years.
  - Reverend Robert James, 1920-1928 (Box 1)
  - Reverend Solomon Ross, 1929-1968 (Box 1)
  - Reverend William Crews, 1969-1990 (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
- Topical File
  The Topical Files cover news articles, a record of deceased members, and a legal dispute with Reverend Knox.
  - Dispute involving Reverend Harold Knox, 2005-2007 (Box 2)
  - News Articles, 1945 (Box 2)
  - The Saints Beyond, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (record of deceased members)
- Miscellaneous Records
  The Miscellaneous Records series covers the years from 1971 to 2003 and documents various special events and sermons held at the church.
  - 1971-1980 (Box 2)
  - 1981-1989 (Box 2)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - 1996-2000 (Box 2)
  - 2001 (Box 2)
  - 2002 (Box 2)
  - 2003 (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)